<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The letters pattents of the Kings declaration for the referring of the generall assemblie of the princes, cardinals, dukes and peeres as well ecclesiasticall as temporall, the officers of the crowne, the lords, gentlemen, officers and others, vnto the 15. day of March next comming. Also to reclaime his subiects and rebellious townes to his obedience. Published in the Parliament of Caen the 22. of of [sic] December. 1589. Faithfullie translated out of the French copie printed at Caen.</title>
            <author>France. Sovereign (1589-1610 : Henry IV)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02972</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13113</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115903</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851120</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851120</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16378</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02972)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16378)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 710:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The letters pattents of the Kings declaration for the referring of the generall assemblie of the princes, cardinals, dukes and peeres as well ecclesiasticall as temporall, the officers of the crowne, the lords, gentlemen, officers and others, vnto the 15. day of March next comming. Also to reclaime his subiects and rebellious townes to his obedience. Published in the Parliament of Caen the 22. of of [sic] December. 1589. Faithfullie translated out of the French copie printed at Caen.</title>
                  <author>France. Sovereign (1589-1610 : Henry IV)</author>
                  <author>Henry IV, King of France, 1553-1610. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Orwin for Augustine Lawton, dwelling in Maiden lane neere Woodstreete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1590]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Henry IV, 1589-1610 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16378:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16378:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>The Kings Declaration, Importing a Reuocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all ſuch Letters for <hi>Enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment, as haue not been verified in the</hi> Chamber of accountes of Normandy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo of all ſuch as haue been graunted to</hi> ſuch perſons as haue or yet do beare armes againſt his Maieſtie, and fauour Rebelles.</p>
            <p>Together with an Arreſt or decree <hi>of the Court of Parliament of</hi> Caen, <hi>concerning</hi> the reſidence of Clergie men vpon their <hi>Cures, and the warrantiſe of their Tithes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faithfully tranſlated out of French according to the <hi>Coppye printed at</hi> Caen.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed for <hi>Edward White,</hi> and are to <hi>be ſold at the little North door of S.</hi> Paules Church, at the ſigne of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:16378:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16378:2"/>
            <head>The Kings Declaration, impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>a rouocation of all ſuch Letters for Enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               </hi>bliſhment, as haue not been verified in the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of account of Normandy, alſo of all ſuch <hi>as haue been graunted to ſuch perſons as haue or yet doo beare armes againſt his Maieſtie, and fauour the Rebels.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="text_of_document">
               <opener>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Enry</hi> by the grace of God, King of <hi>Fraunce</hi> and <hi>Nauarre,</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <salute>to our truſty and welbeloued, our Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of accompts, now tranſfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Caen</hi> greeting and goodwill.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>Wheras the late our moſt honorable Lo. and Brother vpon the neceſsitie of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of this kingdome, thought good to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce vnto the ſtate of Nobilitye, ſundrye pezants, ſome for money, others in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of their ſeruice: the generall Edicts wherof were directed to our Chambers of accounts, to the which eſpecially the verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the ſaid ennoblishments, alſo of the money or deſert of the gift thereof doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine, and without the which verification which is the proper eſſence of the ſaid enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishments, the ſame are of no force or va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lew. Notwithſtanding ſome of our Subiects
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16378:3"/> in the ſaid Court of <hi>Normandy,</hi> pretending that they haue obtained the ſaide Letters of ennoblishment, which they haue not verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before you, do vſurpe the qualitie &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilidges of Nobility, and ſome that were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to tallages, do cauſe themſelues to be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out of the role, to the great preiudice of our treaſurye, and ſuch our Subiectes as doo beare their taxes contrary to all equitye and reaſon.</p>
               <p>Alſo of thoſe that haue beene ennobled or haue verrified their Charters after the forme accuſtomed, ſome haue very ingratefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoulted from our ſeruice.</p>
               <p>We therfore deſiring for the wealth of our eſtate, or the releefe of our poore people, to prouide againſt the fraud and abuſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the obtaining of the ſaide enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishments, as well to the detriment of our treaſurie, as the vnworthineſſe of thoſe who by ſurpriſe rebellion or otherwiſe, haue pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed the gift therof: and hauing referred the matter to the deliberation of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, by the aduice therof we haue ſaid, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ordained, and doo ſay, declare, and
<pb facs="tcp:16378:3"/> ordain by theſe preſents, that all &amp; euery the ſaid ennoblishments heretofore by our ſayd predeceſſor and vs graunted throughout our Cuntry or Dutchye of <hi>Normandy,</hi> which yet are not verified in our ſaide Chamber of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts of <hi>Normandy</hi> to be voide or of none effect. Willing and charging you moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely to inhibit and in our name to forbid all purchaſers of the ſame, neuer to make any vſe therof, neither to take or vſurp the ſayde qualitye or priuiledge of Nobility: alſo all our Iudges or Officers, not to receiue or tollerate them, vntill they haue been well and duelye verified in our ſaid Chamber, vnder pain of tranſgreſsion of falshood &amp; arbitrary amends albeit there should chaunce to be ſome that haue not been directed therto, which as wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and not duely verified we haue and do reuoke.</p>
               <p>We do moreouer forbid our elect and the Controuler in matter of aide and tallages, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye one in his election, that they shall not ſuffer or permit any of the ſaide pretended ennobled Perſons, that hath heretofore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to our tallages, to be raſed out of the
<pb facs="tcp:16378:4"/> rules of the ſame: alſo that if any haue been ſo blotted out and raced, our pleaſure is, that they shall be put in againe and taxed as afore time, vnder paine that themſelues shall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for it in their own priuate name.</p>
               <p>Moreouer to the end to vnderſtand how they haue done their dueties herein, we doo commaund them to preſent vnto you the catalogue and roale of ſuch as pretend them ſelues to be ennobled in euery election, that at the inſtance of our Atourney general they maye be aſsigned in our ſaide Chamber, to bring in their Letters, which if the caſe ſo fall out shall be retained as being obteined by fraude and contrary to the intent of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor and vs, or els in verrification to taxe them as you shall think reaſonable.</p>
               <p>Futhermore, concerning thoſe that vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye haue ſince theſe Nobles reuolted from our ſeruice: we haue and doo reuoke all and euery their charters, graunts that haue beene made vnto them, and all verifications that thereof maye haue enſued: and as men for their rebellion depriued and diſgraded from all honor and degree of nobility, our will is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16378:4"/> that they be ſet down and made contributo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to our tallages as other Pezants are, or in caſe they inhabit in the free towns, they shal not take or attribute to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues any further ſtate or priuiledge then of Pezants, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding whatſoeuer their Letters of grace, either alreadye or hereafter to be purchaſed at our hands, before the ſame haue beene ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in our ſaid Chambers of accompts.</p>
               <p>We doo alſo will and commaund you to cauſe theſe Letters of declaration to be read, published, regiſtred, printed and ſent to all our Seas, auditories, and other places conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient: alſo to cauſe the contents in the ſame to be maintained, kept, and obſerued by Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifs, Stewards, elect, and others our Officers and Subiects, and to proceed againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringers thereof by all due and reaſonable meanes. For this end we giue you full power and authoritie: for ſuch is our pleaſure.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Giuen at our Campe at <hi>Mante</hi> 
                     <date>the 29. of Iune, the yeer of grace 1591. and of our raign the 2.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="endorsement">
               <p>Signed by the King in his counſell Potier, and ſealed with the great ſeale vpon a ſingle labell of yellow waxe.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:16378:5"/>
               <p> Moreouer vpon the ſaide Letters it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, read, published, and regiſtred in the Chamber of accounts of <hi>Normandy,</hi> in the hearing and at the requeſt of the Kings At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney Generall in the ſame, like as is contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the regiſter at <hi>Caen</hi> the 27. of Iulye in the yeere 1591.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Signed <hi>Richer.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="ancillary_document">
               <p>THe Chamber hauing ſeene the Letters pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Kings declaration, giuen at his Campe at Mante the 29. of Iune laſt, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a reuocation of ennobliſhments graunted by the ſaid Lord and the late King, not verified in the ſaid Chamber, vntill the ſaide verification in the ſame, albeit there may be ſome whoſe letters haue not beene directed thereto. Alſo that concerning ſuch as vngratefullye haue reuolted ſince the late troubles: his Maieſtie hath likewiſe reuoked their charters and grauntes, together with all the verri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications that may haue enſued, and that as men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued and for their rebellion diſgraded from all honor and degree of nobility: he willeth them to be reduced and ſuborned to the tallages as other the Pezants are, or if they inhabite in anye free Townes, they ſhall not take vpon them anye other degree or priuelidge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pezants, notwithſtanding whatſoeuer Letters of grace they haue, or heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may obtaine of his ſaide Maieſtie, vnleſſe the firſt verified in the ſaid Chamber, as more at large is conteined in the ſaid letters pattents. The Kings
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16378:5"/> Attorney generall being heard, who hath requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the regiſtring of the ſame, and the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered: The Chamber hath ordained and dooth ordaine, that the ſaide Letters of declaration of the 29. of Iune laſt, ſhalbe read, publiſhed and regiſtred in the roules therof. The Vidimus whereof ſhalbe ſent to the Baylifs and their lieuetenants in euerye Vicounty, alſo to the elect of the election of this Prouince, that there they may likewiſe be read and publiſhed in their Sea and auditories, withall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning the ſubſtitutes of the ſaid Attorney gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in euery the ſaid ivriſdictions, to aſsiſt the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the ſaid Letters, and the ſaid lieuetenants of Bailifs and the elect, to ſend within one moneth into the ſaide Chamber, a roule and catalogue of ſuch perſons as may haue proſecuted their letters of ennobliſhment before them, or that manifeſtly haue taken vpon them the ſaide title and degree of nobility, ſince the yeere 1574. Together with a ſummary of their behauiours, dealinges and reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: alſo to ſend the coppies of their letters and charters obteined by the ſaide ennobled perſons and of the arreſts of verification thereof enſuing.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Giuen <date>the 27. of iuly. 1591.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="endorsement">
               <p>Taken out of the Regeſter of the Chamber of accounts of Normandy.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Signed Richer.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:16378:6"/>
            <head>An Arreſt or decree of the Courte of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Caen concerning the reſidence of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>rats and Clergie men, vpon their Cures, and the warrantiſe of their Tythes.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="text_of_document">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon requeſt exhibited by the Kings Attorney generall, ſhewing that he vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth that in diuers places and pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of this prouince of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy, there are riſen ſundrye Souldiours &amp; other vnknown perſons in armes, who by plaine force doo ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to gather and take vp the tithes of the ſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes (malgre thoſe to whom by right they do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine) to the great preiudice of the Clergie, and contrary to the Kings Edicts and decrees: with all requiring the ſaid Court to graunt him commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to enforme againſt the tranſgreſſors of the ſaide Edictes and decrees, as alſo that the ſame maye be read againe and publiſhed euen in the Pulpits of the ſaid pariſhes: likewiſe in the meane time that all men may be inhibited and forbidden not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude themſelues to diſturb the ſaid Clergie, in the receipt of their ſaid titles, vnder ſuch penalties as by the ſaid Court ſhalbe thought conuenient, na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to anſwere all charges, damages and intereſt of the ſaid Clergie and their farmers.</p>
               <p>The Court hauing ſeen the ſaid requeſt, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen attendance to the Counſellor that made the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte, all thorowly conſidered. The ſaide Court miniſtring Iuſtice vpon the peticion of the ſayde Attorney generall, hath ordeined and enioyned all
<pb facs="tcp:16378:6"/> Curates and Eccleſiaſticall perſons that haue cure of Soules, to be actually reſident vpon their Cures and Benefices, there to preach and teach the word of God, and to inſtruct their Pariſhioners in their due obedience to the King, to pray for his perſon, with the proſperitie of his affaires and eſtate, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey and fulfil his Edicts and the decrees and arreſts of the ſaide Courte, vpon the penaltyes in the ſame ſet down. And in ſo dooing the ſaide Court inbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biteth and forbiddeth all perſons of whatſoeuer eſtate or calling, not to intrude themſelues directly or indirectly, to moleſt or hinder the ſaid Curates or Eccleſiaſticall perſons in the enioying of their Cures or benefices, or in the receipt of their Tithes or reuenues of the ſame, vnder paine of confiſcati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of body and goods. And to the end this preſent decree may be known to all men, the ſaide Courte hath ordained that it ſhalbe ſent into all the Bayly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicks of this reſort, withal enioyning the Bailifs, their Lieuetenants, and the ſaid Attorney generals ſubſtitutes to cauſe it to be publiſhed by ſound of Trumpet in all the accuſtomed places depending of their iuriſdictions, namely in the Pulpets at the great parochiall maſſes in euery Parriſh, vpon the Sunday and other ſolemne feaſtes, to the end none may be exerciſed vpon any pretence of ignorance.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Giuen at Caen in the ſaid Court of Parliament <date>the 7. of Auguſt. 1591.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Signed Donneſt.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="license">
               <pb facs="tcp:16378:7"/>
               <p>IN the ſame yeere 1591. vpon Monday the 12. of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt at <hi>Caen</hi> in the preſence of vs <hi>Iohn Vauquelin</hi> Eſquir, Counſellor to the King &amp; Lieutenant Generall to the L. Bayly of <hi>Caen,</hi> the contents of the areſt aboue mentioned, was read and publiſhed in the audience of the iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid Bailiwick and perſidiall Sea ſitting and by vs holden. It was alſo ordeined at the petition of the kings Attorney generall, that the ſame ſhalbe alſo read and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed with ſound of Trumpet, and common proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all the quarters and places vſed for Proclamations in the ſaid Town, alſo that the copies or Vidimus ſhall be ſent into all other the Vicountyes of this Bayliwick, there to doo the like: alſo to all the Curates and Vickers of the pariſhe of this Vicounty, to the end they may read the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Pulpits of their ſayd pariſhes vpon the Sondaye, or other ſolemne feaſts, that none maye pretend cauſe of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance: alſo that to the ſame ende the ſaide arreſt ſhall be printed.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe all Sergeants are enioyned each within his precinct, to ſee to the fulfilling hereof, vnder the penalties ſet down therfore to make ſuch diſpatch as may be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite or neceſſary therto.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Giuen as aforeſaid.</dateline> 
                  <signed>Signed, <hi>Vauquelin de la Serre.</hi> Criquet.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="license">
               <p>THe ſame day and yeer the contents aboue mentioned were read and publiſhed in the quarters &amp; places ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to make proclamations in tnis Towne of <hi>Caen,</hi> by me <hi>Simon Berot</hi> Sergeant royall of <hi>Caen,</hi> in the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of <hi>Florimont le Soef</hi> ordinary Trompet of the ſame town.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Signed. <hi>Berot.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16378:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
